There's this odd style of fasting that
indicates a serious benefit in removing
visceral fat from the body. Why visceral
fat? Well, visceral fat is a type of fat
that sits around your organs. Think your
kidneys, liver, heart, and so on. And
it's been linked to several diseases. In
fact, we've discussed that harmful
relationship in the past. Briefly, in
that study, the researchers identified a
relationship between type 2 diabetes as
well as coronary artery disease and
visceral fat. That means that the more
visceral fat, the worse the risk of both
diseases. If you've been following my
content weekly
weekly
If you've been following the content
lately, you'll also know there are many,
many ways
If you've been following the content
lately, you'll also know that there are
many, many ways that visceral fat is
harmful to our health. I won't
relitigate things here, but it's
overwhelming, and I certainly plan on
covering more in the future. Anyway,
researchers want us to know what happens
when people use a simple but
unconventional fasting method to
eliminate that harmful visceral fat. In
that study, participants were randomly
told to follow a fasting protocol or a
healthy nutrition. We'll get into what
both of those are in a minute. I kind of
awkwardly phrased that. Participants
were randomly told makes it sound like
they were having a conversation about
something completely different, and then
the information was sprung on them.
Yeah, I told her like, "Don't put the
belts on that side of the closet. It's
just so hard to reach. Like, I have such
trouble reaching that point." Fasting
condition. The point being, they were
randomly allocated to one condition or
another. Okay, the fasting protocol
initially started as two protocols and
then merged into one. So, I'm going to
focus on the one that was used
throughout the study, which is a 36-hour
fast including a protein pacing period.
To get into that a bit more, the
participants fasted for 36 hours, and
within that fasting period, they
consumed a single 400-calorie snack
filled with antioxidants, adaptogens,
and an assortment of different food
items. That's part of the oddity of this
fast. It's more of a quasi fast, but the
results speak for themselves, as we'll
see.
The other oddity of this fast was the
protein pacing period. During the
protein pacing period, which occurred
outside of the 36-hour fast, the
participants consumed four to five meals
per day that were relatively evenly
spaced, and every meal contained
protein. Here's the breakdown. So,
breakfast, a protein shake plus fruit
and vegetables. For lunch, another
protein shake, then a snack that was
only for men. There was a 200-calorie
snack, then dinner, a whole food dinner,
and then an evening snack, which is a
protein snack amounting to around 200
calories. The overall calorie and
macronutrient breakdown was on
non-fasting days around 1,350 calories
for women and 1,700 calories for men. At
a ratio of 35% protein, 35%
carbohydrates, and 30% dietary fat. As
for the comparison diet, which was
labeled as heart-healthy, 1,200 calories
for women, 1,500 calories for men, 50 to
60% carbohydrates, less than 35% dietary
fat, and the rest being protein, usually
around 15%. They also limited their
sugar consumption to less than 50 g and
consumed 20 to 30 g of fiber. Okay, I
think we've set things up suitably. It's
a little out there, but let's look at
what happens. And then, there's some
additional considerations here that we
need to get into as well.
If you're interested in more details on
the study, a written out protocol, and
even an analysis on another study
looking at heart health using an even
easier fasting protocol, check out the
Physionic Insiders Research Platform. I
have a lot more details in there and a
lot more of all this kind of stuff
there. Plus, if you want a supportive
community or to discuss in live sessions
with me, that's also included. Link to
join is in the description box.
Here we go. We're looking at visceral
fat from the beginning of the study at
week zero to the end of the study, week
nine. I'll speak to the length and size
of the study in a bit. For now, we can
appreciate that the dark line, which is
the calorie-restricted, heart-healthy
control group experienced some visceral
fat loss, but the intermittent fasting
group doubled the visceral fat loss on
an absolute basis. So, we know that
visceral fat was lost at quicker rate
using the fasting protocol. But, can we
really attribute it this to the fasting
protocol? There are possible
explanations for these differences that
we should explore. And when we do,
there's actually a mystery that emerges.
So, two logical places to look to
explain these differences might be to
look at energy intake and physical
activity, the inbound and the outgoing
energy.
And when looking at both energy intake
and energy expenditure by physical
activity, there was no differences
between the groups. The fasting group
did consume slightly more dietary fiber,
but not much. And of course, by design,
the fasting group also consumed much
more protein. So, could there be a
metabolism effect going on here
independent of physical activity?
Possibly. So, some people focus more on
insulin as opposed to calories, but here
again, insulin levels were about the
same. In fact, the ending insulin level
may have been slightly higher in the
fasting group. So, a bit of a mystery on
exactly how this all happens, but there
is one distinct possibility, increases
in metabolism, which wasn't measured,
unfortunately. Now, the study was in
relatively healthy, overweight
individuals, and as you might have
noticed, the study was only eight to
nine weeks long, included a small group
of people, around 20 per condition. So,
one critique could be that this might
only apply to those individuals, and
that's possible without further data.
However, I'm skeptical this would only
work for those individuals. In addition,
the duration of the study is what makes
it exciting. Getting these effects in
just two months really speaks to its
effectiveness.
In the end, the takeaway here is that
this 36-hour quasi fast including 400
calories of nutrients plus a protein
pacing period during the other five to
six days significantly outperformed a
heart-healthy, calorie-restricted diet
by a sizable amount when looking to
eliminate as much harmful visceral fat
as possible. But, assuming that you want
to be consuming more food and still pack
a punch on your visceral fat, there's
other ways of attacking the issue, which
I describe right here. Thanks for tuning
in, and I'll catch you over there. Bye.